这是我爹
他就要完成他最近一直在忙的一项工作啦 就是 詹姆斯韦伯太空望远镜!
以下简称"JWST"
JWST的遮阳罩~
大家好 我是《天天大聪明》频道的Destin
JWST就要上天啦
这可是全球科学界一直心心念念的大事
反正我做字幕的时候还没(
等大家刷到这个视频的时候 可能它已经上天了
甚至可能已经在轨运行多年了
不过这不重要 因为我今天要与一位特别的人对话 并学习很多JWST相关的内容
JWST(部署后)体积过大 无法装进任何火箭整流罩
所以为了把它送到太空 必须先把它折叠成更紧凑的形状
发射后 它会像折纸作品一样慢慢展开
而在我眼里 这简直是设计精妙的工程奇迹
你不但要保证这一系列流程都能顺利完成
还要保证这些结构能经受火箭发射时剧烈的震动环境
像JWST这样规模的工程
不但立项和制造要花很久 任务执行也要相当久 简直叹为观止
大家刚刚已经见过我爹了 即使他不在这干活我也会为JWST感到震撼的
但他的努力让我更加觉得这件事有着特别的意义
而下期视频我将详细讲讲我爹具体在遮阳罩上做了哪些工作
因为真的太牛逼了 有太多值得学习的东西了
但首先我想先了解一下JWST到底是什么 它的各项重要内容是如何完成的
我们要找一位大佬聊聊这些
2017年的时候我很荣幸到了戈达德太空飞行中心
又极其幸运得以和一位在这个项目里工作的大佬进行对话
这位大佬就是约翰·马瑟博士
在对话开始之前 我想先向大家介绍一下这位大佬
如果你想从全人类里挑一个人给你介绍JWST
那你肯定会选约翰·马瑟博士
原因其一 他是一位天体物理学家和宇宙学家
他还凭借和George Smoot在宇宙背景探测者卫星的工作获得了诺贝尔物理奖
我想表达的是 没有人比他更懂头顶这片星空了
而天文学家们一直在苦苦寻找膨胀宇宙的中心 却一直毫无踪迹
想象一个无限的宇宙正在无限地向自己扩张
没有边界 没有中心 也没有边缘
原因其二 他是整个JWST项目的首席科学家
这意味着他代表着科学侧的利益 来担任项目首席科学家
而鉴于他脑中所知道的东西 也鉴于整个项目都是科研相关的
大家就能想象他的意见有多么重要了
不只是因为我们在和一个充满智慧的灵魂对话 他还非常善良
比如我做采访的时候 其实那次采访并不是做过的最好的
我当时在一个小会议中心的边屋 想要拍他 但我的相机一直在过热
而他则非常耐心 希望大家也能这样耐心
他的解释真的很通俗易懂
我们在用最简单的语言去解释人类建造过的最复杂的东西
稍后的对话过程中我会中间插几句话 还会简单画两笔~挺有意思的
那么我们开始吧
我们去和参与建造JWST的伟大灵魂对话吧~让我们走进本期《天天大聪明》~
那么这位就是约翰·马瑟博士啦
-我可以称呼您尊敬的诺奖得主吗? -可以呀
-您愿意和我们讲讲JWST吗? -我很乐意 -我们坐下聊吧
我想做的是 在您同意的情况下 做一个关于JWST的系列视频
OK~
-而您就是JWST的幕后大佬? -呃……我只是参与者之一
我从项目一开始就是首席项目科学家了
您的大名吾辈早有耳闻 为人谦逊 从不居功自傲
我的确为我们所做的事情感到自豪 但显然这是一个团队项目 非常庞大的团队项目
这就是望远镜的外形图啦 你可以看到……
它看起来完全不像一个望远镜 既不像当年伽利略用过的那款 也不像哈勃望远镜
远远待在太空 更像是一个汇聚太阳能的东西
它有着巨大的六边形主镜 由18块小六边形组成
用来收集我笔指的方向来的遥远星系的光
经过主镜反射 再经过这里的一块小凸面镜反射 回到这里黑色的部分
而这里是设备组件的起点
这种结构是叫卡塞格兰反射镜吗?
这两部分构成了卡塞格兰反射镜
这里面还有第三块镜子 图里看不到
构成一套三反射镜消像散望远镜 性能更好
抱歉我没听清?
三反射镜消像散系统
这我得好好查查
这样的系统可以有更大的有效视场
懂了
这点对我们很重要 因为我们想要更好的成像质量 又有这么大的反射镜
我回来的确查了一下这个东西
三反射镜消像散系统 Three-mirror anastigmat
简单来讲 光在到达拍摄的传感器之前会经过三次反射
每次反射都有专门的目的
第一块主镜 就像大水桶一样
把来自宇宙的各种光都收集起来并汇聚
所以他们希望这块镜子越大越好
因为更大的面就能收集更多的光
从巨大的主镜反射来的光会汇聚到它前面的一块很小的二级镜面上
你们想想这一大块主镜能比二级的小镜子多收集多少宇宙里的光
所有光会反射进望远镜内 经过三级镜面的反射后来到微调镜上
这块镜子会补偿航天器移动带来的误差 功能类似相机的稳定器
经过这一切光学组件后 就到了整个三反射镜消像散系统得到图像的地方了
虽然叫"三反射镜"消像散系统 但其实里面有第四个反射镜充当稳定器 懂了吧
建造最难的地方就是这块巨大的主镜
因为它由18块小镜子组成
全部要在望远镜进入太空后再调整到正确的位置
它们都是由铍制造的 非常轻 非常坚硬 且在低温下不会变形
最难的地方也正在此 因为我们要让它非常非常非常轻
每一小块六边形镜面 都轻到用手就能提起来
如果我们让你上手的话
所以它们的材料真的又薄又精确
在镜面部分后 是设备组件
里面有相机和光谱仪
为了这两样东西我们还研发了一堆新玩意
我们之前需要更高标准的检测器
而检测器有两种重要原料 一种叫碲镉汞 一种叫掺砷硅
这两种物质可以让我们的研究有更高的灵敏度 更广范围的波长
-而这些东西之前都还不存在? -存在倒是存在 但达不到我们的需求
灵敏度不够 尺寸太小
所以这方面研发投入了不少
另一个显而易见的难点就是这么大一块东西该怎么造?
我指的这块 就是遮阳罩
由五层镀有金属的塑料膜组成
聚酰亚胺?
对 所以太阳光是从下面照过来的 就全反射走了
只有极少数的热量会渗透过来 我们想让望远镜保持低温 保持稳定
所以到了太空望远镜的飞行姿态大概是这样 太阳一直照着它底面的设备组件
光学镜面部分保持在阴影中
就好像在地球上我们只能在星球阴影中 也就是晚上才能看到星星
而这块巨大的遮阳罩也能为望远镜营造出持续的"夜晚"环境
望远镜的一侧一直在黑暗中 另一侧一直面对太阳
这样做会带来很多有趣的事情
因为通常航天器都要做好温度控制 保持一切设备在正确温度下
而当光学元件保持低温的时候 就再也不用担心它的温度波动了
这样把它设定到目标温度后就可以让它开始干活了
而这会带来很多有趣的工程上的难题 我们会在未来几章的视频中提到
相对平凡一点的东西 就是面向太阳一侧的东西了
遮阳罩这边有元件舱 有航电 供电 发动机 燃料罐 无线电收发装置和计算机
各种维持望远镜运营的东西都在这边
固定航天器姿态也是在这边吗? 比如说动量轮?
对 动量轮也在这边 用来让望远镜指向特定方向
这还有火箭发动机 有两个作用
一方面是维持轨道 因为它的轨道是不稳定轨道
另一方面是要卸载动量轮 因为动量轮会一直积累角动量
而那些角动量是哪来的? 是太阳光
它会轻微推动望远镜 导致它不平衡
所以这两件事让望远镜需要燃料维持
而这也决定了这架望远镜的观测寿命
刚刚那段信息量不小 但我相信大家能听懂
我慢慢讲
动量轮 可老厉害了
我几年前做过一期很细致的视频讲这个 但其大致思想
就是不用火箭发动机就能让航天器保持一定指向 像空中的猫一样
av16647535
强烈建议回头看看那个视频
一提到动量轮 我经常举的例子是摩托车
这段远古视频就能很好说明
摩托车运动员腾空的时候
就相当于处于失重状态
但骑手可以通过拉刹车或者轰油门来控制自己抬头还是压低
如果他们轰油门 车头就会拉起
因为后轮的旋转会给车一个相反方向的扭矩
如果车手想低头 拉刹车就好了 后轮转速降低 车身就会压低
放在太空望远镜上也是一样的道理
不过上面装的不是摩托车
而是几个不同方向持续旋转的电子飞轮
控制它们旋转的加速减速
就能把角动量转递给整个望远镜
几个飞轮的转速控制组合起来就能精确控制整个航天器的指向
JWST的另一个有趣的冷知识是我们虽然想让它指向特定方向
但它却持续会受到太阳方向的压力
成为太阳光压
简单来讲就是太阳发出的光和各种电磁波会打在望远镜上
会给望远镜施加一个压力 有点像帆船
这个压力非常非常小
一平米的面积大概只有千分之一克的数量级
但在太空里 真空的零重力环境下 再微小的力也能影响很多事情
这是绝对不能忽视的
来到望远镜的背后 这段黑色的部分 图里看不到
主镜背面是一大块的设备组件
包括相机和光谱仪
可覆盖频段从人眼能看到的0.6微米波长的可见光
到人眼不可见的波长28微米的红外光
博士刚刚说到光谱仪波长范围从0.6微米到28微米
指的是望远镜能探测到的波长范围
这意味着望远镜只能看到可见光中红色的部分
同时还能继续看到红外波段的内容
选择观测如此大范围的红外波段 肯定是出于某种考虑
而博士稍后也会提到这些
所以我们还有光谱仪 能探测到星光中的各种颜色分量
从观测到的结果来了解物体内部发生了什么
首先我们想知道的是它是由什么物质组成的
所以要找的是谱线
而谱线来自于不同化学元素 不同分子
就好像7月4号五颜六色的烟花一样 每种都是来自不同的物质
-但这不太一样吧 因为光谱会红移吧？ -没错
那您是怎么知道红移后的光谱是自己想找的东西？
我们实际上找的是某种特定的图案
如果看到的是单独一条谱线 那你没法百分之百确认是什么物质
所以真想百分之百确定观测到的是什么物质 就必须找两条或更多的谱线
而这也说明了一个事实 就是那些正在靠近我们或者远离我们的物体
都实实在在参与了整个宇宙的膨胀 而这会大幅度改变我们观测到的波长
远离我们的物体 观测到的波长会变长
这个波长的变化就叫红移
可以是零 如果物体在向我们移动那还可以是负的 还可以是很大的数字
我们曾经用望远镜观测到的最大红移是11
意思是我们观测到的波长是它发出的光的波长的12倍
-哦所以这个数字是倍数关系? -没错
所以比如说莱曼谱线阿尔法 波长是0.12微米
等我们观测到的时候已经变成1.44微米了
这也是为什么红外波段观测如此重要
因为各种观测结果都会红移
没错 所以想要观测各种对象都被红移了的遥远宇宙
就必须有一台红外望远镜 才能研究那些早期是紫外光波段的目标
我插一句 您刚刚说红移了11倍波长
是不是意味着望远镜上的传感器能探测到超过11倍波长的范围?
是的 而这也取决于观测物体发出光时的波长
如果是某个特定的谱线 比如氢原子的莱曼阿尔法谱线 红移11倍
那就是原来波长的11倍 1.44微米
但如果假定宇宙中有更远的物体存在
那我们就能看到更大程度的红移
我们目前预期目标是想看到红移20-30倍的物体
-你是不是特别期待? -那是相当期待啊!
目前还没人观测到 但预测是存在的
我们对其中某些预测还是很有信心的
好吧 我的相机又过热了
但现在咱们刚好可以聊聊红移
其实大家都体验过汽车喇叭的多普勒效应
当救护车或者汽车鸣笛向你驶来的时候
你会听到稍高的声调 但当汽车远离你的时候 声调就会降低
当声源向你移动的时候 声波等效于被压缩
所以你耳朵听到的结果就是频率变高
而声源远离你的时候 声波就等效于被拉伸 听起来频率就会变低
对于光来说也是同理
对于一个远离我们的恒星发出的光来说 我们看到的光等效于被拉伸
就像汽车喇叭声调降低一样
观测到的光的频率也会降低 会从可见光波段降低到红外波段
所以如果我们看去观测红外波段
就相当于看不到那些原本发出可见光、在远离我们的星星
这就是红移
而对于持续膨胀的宇宙来说
我们观测到的很多物体都在慢慢远离我们
因此观测红外波段是非常重要的
- So this is a giant tripod. There's three legs.
The hinge points here, here, here, here,
and this leg folds in half.
And here's a hinge point.
So to get this ready for launch
we pull this one out sideways.
So you can pull the mirror up here and the legs
actually fold around behind the observatory.
So it just fits.
- [Destin] You had a glimmer in your eye when you said that.
That's a big deal. - That's a big deal.
And it's one of many things
that have to work when you launch.
Of course, everything is folded up for launch.
Everything has to unfold and do the right thing out there.
So of course the big question everyone has is
are you sure it's going to work?
And the answer is, so of course you can't be sure.
But we are doing what we should be doing to make sure.
So what do you do?
Well, number one, you have two of everything
when you possibly can.
So you get two shots when you need them.
You rehearse everything.
You practice and practice and practice.
And you have grouchy people come to tell you
when you're not doing it right.
That's really important because we hate doing it wrong
even if we don't like being told.
- [Destin] What are those people?
The quality assurance officers?
- Those are review panels. We get peer reviews.
We get senior engineers that have done
something related before that have
a good instinct about these things.
They say, "No, don't do it like that. Do it some other way."
But the most important thing is you test and test and test.
Because there's no such thing as analyzing anything
well enough that you can be sure.
- [Destin] You know, you have destructive tests
and non-destructive tests.
So how do you perform a test
when you only have one test article?
- Well, we actually made several test articles.
We made a pathfinder for the telescope
with the carbon fiber framework and we put on
two of the mirrors or even finally three.
- And my camera overheated again.
At this point, I'm starting to get embarrassed,
but don't worry about it, this gives us an opportunity
as the camera cools off to get distracted
by cool things at NASA.
This interview took place at NASA's
Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Maryland,
which is where they've been controlling
the Hubble Space Telescope for the last several decades.
I spoke to the Hubble operations manager
and got to see the actual control room.
That's a topic for another day,
but they do all kinds of awesome stuff here at Goddard.
So you're gonna make this Space Telescope
and you're gonna put it up into space, you don't want
the first time it sees a vacuum or near absolute zero
on the sensor side, you don't want that to happen
for the first time in space so you got to
try to simulate that on earth.
How do you do these incredibly physically challenging things
here on one atmosphere on the surface of earth?
The answer is a huge thermal vacuum that was built
at Goddard back in the 1960s.
And it's incredible.
- [Darryl] So basically a large vacuum
and they pump liquid nitrogen into it.
- [Destin] To make it cold?
- [Darryl] Make it cold, make it simulate
the environment of space.
- [Destin] That's crazy.
So this is how you simulate space on the ground.
- That's right. This is what it takes.
- [Destin] That's amazing.
- [Darryl] I love the legacy look of it.
- [Destin] It looks like a boiler, but backwards.
It's made to keep pressure out instead of contain pressure.
- [Darryl] All designed on paper back in the sixties.
Think about it, like, that's all analog.
- [Destin] Okay, so we're on the top floor now.
We are walking towards
the top of the thermal vacuum chamber.
That's cool. So do they actually put James Webb in there?
- Some of the components.
Before they assemble it they would take
some of the large components into this on.
And then we have much smaller ones over there.
They test everything all the way down to the nuts and bolts.
These are also thermal vacuum chambers, just smaller scale.
- [Destin] Oh, this is for component level stuff. Gotcha.
- [Darryl] Nuts and bolts.
- [Destin] Nuts and bolts.
- [Darryl] And smaller assembly parts.
- [Destin] Oh, that's cool.
They've got the hydraulic diagram integrated to the valves.
That's pretty neat.
- [Darryl] Where do you think that was printed? Do you know?
- Oh wow. My bad got a little bit distracted.
The next thing they want to test for
are the launch forces that happen on the rocket.
They have a huge centrifuge at Goddard
and they can place instruments on that and simulate
the G-forces that the telescope will see during launch.
It's pretty awesome.
And then there's the vibrations
that'll happen during launch.
This is the shaker table.
So the Aerion is gonna to shake violently.
What you have to do is you have to make sure
that the telescope isn't going to break during launch.
So here at Goddard Space Center, check it out.
It's a really cool area here.
This is the way they test that.
They'll put the telescope here,
they'll mount it in position.
And then they'll shake it violently to make sure
that nothing falls apart, nothing breaks.
Here's some B roll footage of them doing that.
The vibration testing. You can see the telescope shaking.
Okay, I'm in a really neat spot right now.
This is the tent that they move James Webb around with.
It's like a portable clean room.
And this is the sound chamber where
they're gonna acoustically load the thing.
What they're doing here is simulating
the roar of the rockets, which can get up over 140 decibels
and can be very destructive.
So they've got this big chamber with speakers in it,
with a massive subwoofer and other speakers
to blast it with sound.
That's a subwoofer up top?
- This is the largest subwoofer in the country
as far as I know, so if you really wanna drop the base
this is where you come. (Destin laughing)
- The cool thing about a sound chamber is that the sound
is different at different parts in the chamber
because you get reflections and echoes off the wall.
For example, if I have a sound wave going across
and bouncing off the wall, you might get
constructive interference, meaning you get a louder sound
at different points than you might get at quieter spots.
So in order to test that, you can see, they have microphones
hanging at different points in the chamber.
Wow. I'm gonna get back behind this.
Because I don't want to interfere with what they're doing.
These people are moving this tent by hand.
And the way they're doing that is on an air bearing.
They've got compressed air pumped to the feet of the tent
and a really flat surface floor and they're able
to move the whole thing by hand.
Here's a couple of really cool shots
where you can see people moving
the entire space telescope by hand
within the portable cleaning room on a cushion of air.
Can you imagine what you're thinking? This is so rad.
So my camera's overheating.
Is that a problem on the telescope? (laughs)
- No, the observatory doesn't overheat
because it's facing outer space.
The whole telescope is protected from the sunshine,
from the earth and from the moon all the time
by this giant sun shield.
And we chose the orbit specially so we could do that.
The Lagrange Point Two orbit that we choose is actually
the only place you can go where the single sided umbrella
that we build can protect the observatory completely
from all of those things at the same time.
- Lagrange points are special points in space where
when you have two orbital bodies interacting with each other
there's these little special spots where things
can kind of just balance.
They're right in the sweet spot where they're being pulled
in two different directions at the same time
and they just kind of hover there.
Lagrange points are fascinating.
There are five Lagrangian points
for any combination of two orbital bodies.
Since James Webb sensors could be affected
by earth shine and moon shine, L2 of the earth's sun system
is the optimum place for it to be
and Dr. Mather is about to explain why.
How are you going to communicate with it
if it's on the other side of the moon?
- Oh, it's not. We don't go to that exact spot.
And of course the moon orbits as well.
- [Destin] So are you orbiting a Lagrangian point?
- You orbit around a Lagrange point, we don't go to it.
Number one, it's easier to get there.
Number two, we want points in the shade.
It's actually right behind the earth.
And most of the sunshine is being blocked by the earth
at that spot so you don't want to go there.
- [Destin] Can you draw that for me on this piece of paper?
- Yeah, so, sure. Here's the sun over here.
Here's the earth over here.
And not to scale, but here is the Lagrange point.
And we are going to be orbiting
around a Lagrange point like that.
- [Destin] Just enough to get the sunshine around the earth?
Where's the moon?
- [John] The moon is a lot closer in.
My handwriting is not so good today.
But the Lagrange point's about four times
as far from the earth as the moon is.
- [Destin] Oh, I see.
- [John] So we never have a problem with that.
- [Destin] Gotcha.
I didn't realize that you were choosing the orbit.
I thought the whole point was to, yeah, I guess...
- We need the sunshine.
- [Destin] Why?
- We need solar power to run the observatory.
- [Destin] Okay, I see.
- We need the sunshine. It also takes more fuel to get to.
- [Destin] You don't have an RTG onboard?
- No, we don't. There's no need for it.
And that's hard to do.
So we need several kilowatts of electricity, so sunshine--
- [Destin] Where are the solar panels?
- Solar panels are hidden in this picture, but they are
obviously going to be on the sun side of the big sun shield.
But a few kilowatts is actually small
for a giant observatory.
- [Destin] It is.
- That's 'cause what's over here on this side
doesn't use anything much.
Only a little bit of energy to run the detectors.
- [Destin] I know you're excited
about what's gonna come out of the telescope.
- Yes, indeed.
Who knows what's out there that we've never guessed at?
We have wonderful way exciting things
to work on that we know about.
The first stars and galaxies, the first black holes,
how the galaxies grow, how stars are being born today
with planets around them and even planets around other stars
and the outer solar system, where we learn something
about how solar systems work and maybe even
how come the earth is special or not.
The web telescope will make beautiful pictures as well.
They will be different, of course,
because we pick up light at different wavelengths,
but those beautiful glowing gas clouds,
we'll see them too, just differently.
We are, among other things, trying to see through
those glowing clouds to see what's inside.
So the stars that are being born inside,
you can't see them directly right now because
that dust and gas is obscuring them.
Infrared light that we will pick up can go
right around those dust grains and see inside.
So our hope is that it'll look different and also beautiful.
- [Destin] So you're saying the infrared light
can go through those dust rings?
- [John] Yes, infrared light, well,
all light bounces off dust particles,
but the longer the wavelength, the less bounce.
- [Destin] I see.
- [John] So the infrared light can go through the clouds
that enables us to see things.
- [Destin] Oh, that's a big deal.
So what we'll probably be seeing
is we'll take infrared images and then
we'll false color them so people can see
these beautiful pictures that we've seen in the past.
That's exactly the plan? - Yeah.
- [Destin] That's fantastic. Last question.
What are you gonna do on launch day?
- I'll either be at the launch site to cheer,
or I'll be back here to talk to the public.
Don't know which one will be.
There's such a limited number of people can go
to the launch site that the people who really need
to be there should be there.
- Right, but are you, I mean, that's gotta be
a very anxious moment for you, I'm sure.
- No.
- [Destin] No?
- I don't get anxious about stuff I can't deal with.
- [Destin] Can you kind of tell me why?
- Yeah, so I'm not an anxious about things
because I know that we're doing the right thing
to make the best possible plan.
So when somebody says "We should worry about this,"
we worry about it and then we make a plan.
So when you're 70 years old,
you get tired of worrying about stuff.
You just say, "We'll make a plan."
- [Destin] I see. And you accept what happens.
- Yeah.
- That's interesting. That's interesting.
I really liked that. (laughs)
This is Dr. John Mather and I cannot thank you enough.
- Destin, a pleasure to talk with you
and look forward to seeing what you make.
- I thought this conversation was fascinating
on so many different levels.
I came into it expecting to learn about science
and astronomy and how different things work.
But I left with a sense of, it's like a nugget of wisdom
that Dr. Mather dropped on us there at the end.
Think about it.
This is one of the most complicated things
that humans have ever done.
There's a lot riding on this.
There is a tremendous amount of investment of time,
money, human lives, my family included.
There's a lot riding on this.
But when I asked him, "Well, aren't you worried?"
He said, "No, because I've made the best possible plan.
We've done our best."
And then he just releases it.
He's literally going to let it ride on a rocket.
There's some deep wisdom there
that I'm going to apply to my own life.
If the man that's over one of the most difficult
scientific endeavors that humans have ever done
can make the best possible plan and then not worry
and then emotionally release that to say,
"We did our best. Let's see what happens."
If he can do that with this project,
how can I apply that to my own life?
Anyway, I thought that was amazing.
I thought it was super deep wisdom.
And perhaps that would be helpful for you as it is for me.
In an upcoming video we're gonna learn more
about the James Webb Space Telescope from my dad,
who actually worked on the sun shield.
Very excited to share this with you.
It was exciting for me to be able to go to see my dad
do one of the coolest things that humans have done.
I don't know. And this is my dad, right?
I'm really excited about that.
So I'll share that with you in an upcoming video.
And I hope you enjoyed this interview with Dr. John Mather.
I'm Destin. You're getting smarter every day.
Have a good one. Bye.